things. Nick. Thanks, Inga, and good morning, everyone. I'll start on slide 7 with a recap
of our first quarter sales performance. As Inga mentioned, we posted strong organic growth in
the quarter of 4.6%, with volumes up 4.5% and selling prices up 0.1%. Divestitures of non-strategic
businesses, reduced sales by 0.4 percentage points, and foreign currency translation decreased sales
by another 50 basis points. As a result, total first quarter sales in U.S. dollars increased 3.7%
versus last year. As you can see on the right side of the slide, growth was broad-based across
all geographic areas. Let me start with the U.S., where organic growth was 1.4%,
led by mid-single-digit increases in both industrial and safety and graphics. Our electronics and energy
and healthcare businesses also delivered solid growth in the quarter. The consumer business
declined mid-single digits organically in Q1, impacted by channel adjustments in the office market,
as Inga mentioned. Asia-Pacific led the company with organic growth of 10.1%.
All business groups posted strong growth in the quarter, led by a double-digit increase in
electronics and energy. We also had strong growth in industrial, healthcare, and consumer.
Looking at key countries within Asia-Pacific, organic growth increased 13% in both China, Hong Kong,
and Japan. Excluding our electronics businesses, China-Hong Kong grew 12%, and Japan was up 2%.
Moving to EMEA, organic growth increased 4% in Q1. West Europe was up 5% organically,
with sales growth led by industrial and safety and graphics. Central East Europe and Middle East Africa
grew nearly 2%. Finally, organic growth in Latin America-Canada increased 2.3%, led by a high single-digit
growth in healthcare, along with solid growth in consumer and safety and graphics. At a country level,
Mexico continued to deliver strong growth at 8%. Canada was up 3%, while Brazil declined 3%.
Please turn to slide 8 for the first quarter P&L highlights. Company-wide, first quarter sales
were $7.7 billion, and net income increased 3.7% to $1.3 billion. GAP operating margins were 23.1%,
down 100 basis points versus last year's Q1. Earlier, you heard Inga mention the additional $136 million
of strategic investments we made in Q1 to strengthen 3M for the future, in terms of both growth and
productivity. Excluding the impact of these investments, margins were up 80 basis points
year over year, driven by strong organic growth and solid operational performance.
Let's take a closer look at the various components of our margin performance in the first quarter.
Organic growth, along with improved productivity, contributed 120 basis points to margins.
Lower raw material costs, net of selling price changes, added another 50 basis points.
Raw material prices remained favorable to start the year, as our global businesses again delivered
savings in excess of market price changes.
We expect raw material benefits to moderate as the year progresses, but still remain positive
for the full year.
Turning to headwinds, foreign currency, net of hedge gains, brought margins down 40 basis points
in the quarter.
As previously discussed, strategic investments impacted margins by 180 basis points, and higher pension
and OPEB expense decreased margins by 30 basis points year-on-year.
Finally, lower year-on-year gains from divestitures reduced margins by an additional 20 basis points.
Let's now turn to slide 9 for a closer look at earnings per share.
First quarter, gap earnings increased 5.4% to $2.16 per share.
The combination of organic growth and productivity contributed $0.22 per share to Q1 earnings.
Business transformation is having a positive impact on our productivity efforts.
The year-on-year impact from divestitures reduced earnings by $0.03 per share.
Foreign currency, net of hedging, reduced pre-tax earnings by $0.04 a share, while strategic investments
were a $0.16 impact.
The first quarter tax rate was 23.7% versus 26.8% in the comparable quarter,
which increased earnings by $0.09 per share.
The lower year-on-year tax rate was driven by favorable geographic profit mix,
increased tax benefits from employee equity-based compensation,
and ongoing strategic tax initiatives.
In light of the first quarter performance, we now expect our 2017 full-year tax rate to be in the range of 26% to 27.5%.
Finally, average diluted shares outstanding declined nearly 2% year-on-year,
which added $0.03 to Q1 earnings per share.
Please turn to slide 10 for a look at cash flow.
We continue to generate solid operating cash flow as a company,
which allows us to consistently invest in the business and also return cash back to shareholders.
First quarter free cash flow was $701 million, down $245 million year-on-year,
largely due to the timing of pension contributions.
Full-year 2017 pension contributions are expected to remain in the range of $300 to $500 million,
similar to 2016.
Free cash flow conversion was 53%, and for the full year,
we continue to anticipate free cash flow conversion to be in the range of 95% to 105%.
Recall that Q1 is typically our lowest conversion rate of the year.
First quarter capital expenditures were $287 million,
in line with our expectations heading into the quarter.
For the full year, we continue to anticipate CapEx investments in the range of $1.3 to $1.5 billion.
As you heard earlier, we increased our first quarter per share dividend by 6%,
resulting in $702 million in cash dividends paid to shareholders during the quarter.
We also returned $690 million to shareholders through gross share repurchases.
We continue to expect full-year repurchases in the range of $2.5 to $4.5 billion.
Let's now review our performance by business group, starting with Industrial on slide 11.
Industrial continued its strong growth momentum from Q4,
delivering first quarter sales of $2.7 billion, up 5.7% organically.
Industrial's growth was broad-based across all businesses and geographic areas.
Our automotive OEM business continued to lead sales growth within Industrial,
increasing double digits organically.
Growth in this business outpaced the rate of global car and light truck builds by more than 400 basis points.
Advanced materials also had a strong start to the year, up high single digits.
Our heartlanded businesses within Industrial, abrasives, industrial adhesives and tapes,
and automotive aftermarket, each increased mid-single digits organically.
On a geographic basis, organic growth was led by Asia-Pacific, up high single digits,
while the U.S. and EMEA increased mid-single digits.
Industrial delivered first quarter operating income of $625 million,
with operating margins of 23.1%.
Operating margins were down 80 basis points year-on-year,
or up 40 basis points, adjusting for a Q1 2016 divestiture gain.
As you can see, Industrial is off to a strong start to 2017.
For the full year, we now expect organic growth in the range of 2% to 5%,
versus our prior estimate of 1% to 3%.
Please turn to slide 12.
First quarter sales and safety and graphics were up 4.8% organically, to $1.5 billion.
Personal safety, another heartland business,
delivered strong organic growth in the high single digits,
with particular strength in Asia-Pacific and the U.S.
The Rook and Granules business continued to perform well in the first quarter,
posting double-digit organic growth as demand remained strong in the replacement shingle market.
Geographically, safety and graphics grew organically in all areas,
led by mid-single-digit increases in EMEA, Asia-Pacific, and the U.S.
Operating income for the business group was $399 million,
and operating margins increased 180 basis points to 26.1%.
Adjusting for acquisition and divestiture activity in this year and last,
operating margins were up 80 basis points.
As with Industrial, safety and graphics is off to a strong start,
and growth is better than we anticipated entering the year.
We now expect organic growth for this business to be between 2% and 5%,
versus a prior estimate of 1% to 3%.
Please turn to slide 13.
Our healthcare business generated first-quarter sales of $1.4 billion.
Organic growth was 3.1% year-on-year,
in line with our full-year expectations of 3% to 5%.
Growth was led by a double-digit increase in both drug delivery systems and food safety.
Our medical consumables businesses,
which represent the largest segment within healthcare,
posted good growth in Q1.
Oral care delivered mid-single-digit organic growth in the first quarter,
a marked improvement from the second half of 2016.
Our health information systems business was down low single digits organically.
We expect the business to improve throughout the year.
Geographically, organic growth in healthcare was positive in all areas,
led by high single-digit growth in Latin America, Canada, and Asia Pacific.
We saw notable strength in China-Hong Kong,
which was up double digits in the quarter.
Healthcare's operating income was $434 million,
and margins remained strong at 30.5%.
Importantly, we generated these returns
while investing an additional $21 million
to enhance growth in core platforms across the business.
Please turn to slide 14.
Electronics and energy led our company
with organic growth of 11.5% in the first quarter.
Sales were $1.2 billion.
The electronic side of the business grew 18% organically,
as our team successfully drove increased penetration
on a number of OEM platforms.
Demand strengthened across most market segments
in consumer electronics,
which also boosted our growth rate,
and we benefited from favorable year-on-year comps.
Our energy-related businesses were up 1% organically,
with low single-digit growth in electrical markets,
while telecom was flat.
On a geographic basis,
organic growth was up double digits in Asia Pacific,
where our electronics business is concentrated.
First quarter operating income for electronics and energy
was $225 million,
with margins of 18.6%,
up 70 basis points.
Adjusting for first quarter portfolio actions,
margins were nearly 24%,
up 600 basis points year-on-year.
As you can see,
Q1 organic growth was very robust
for electronics and energy.
As a result,
we are updating our full-year growth expectations
for this business
to a range of up 1% to 6%,
versus a prior range of down 3% to up 1%.
The first half of the year
is expected to be stronger than the second half,
largely driven by year-on-year comps.
Please turn to slide 15.
First quarter sales and consumer were $1 billion,
and organic growth declined 1.2% year-on-year.
Three of our four businesses within consumer
grew organically,
again led by home improvement,
followed by consumer health care and home care.
Within the home improvement business,
our command damage-free mounting products
posted strong double-digit growth
as accelerated investments continued to pay off.
Filtrete filters also delivered strong growth in the quarter.
More than offsetting this growth
was a year-on-year decline
in our stationary and office supplies business,
which was impacted by continued channel inventory reductions,
primarily in the U.S. office retail and wholesale.
Geographically,
organic growth in consumer
was led by Asia Pacific and Latin America Canada,
which was more than offset by a decline in the U.S.
Operating income was $222 million,
with operating margins of 21.3%.
Looking at the full year,
we expect organic growth for consumer
to be in the range of 1% to 3%
versus a prior estimate of 2% to 4%.
We also expect to see growth improve
as the year progresses.
Please turn to slide 16.
Before I turn it back to Inga,
let me address a few items
that we anticipate will happen
over the remainder of 2017.
The net impact of these items
is factored into our EPS guidance today.
First, as you may recall,
in December,
we announced the divestiture
of our identity management business
within Safety and Graphics.
The sale of this business,
which has annual sales
of approximately $205 million,
is expected to close
during the second quarter.
Upon completion,
we expect to record a gain
on sale of approximately $0.55 per share,
partially offset by the profit
that will go with the business in 2017
after the divestiture is closed.
In addition,
recall at our investor meeting
in March of 2016,
we introduced a plan
to better optimize our portfolio
and supply chain footprint.
We expect to make significant progress
on that plan in 2017
with associated costs
in the range of $0.40 to $0.45 per share
over the remainder of the year.
We anticipate $0.20 to $0.30 per share
will incur in Q2.
In total,
the net impact of these items
is expected to add
between $0.05 and $0.10
to 2017 earnings per share.
Again,
this impact is reflected
in our full year updated guidance,
which Inga will now cover
on slide 17.
Inga?
To acknowledge your request.
Yeah, Andy,
thanks for the question.
You covered quite a few things there.
Just from an overall theme standpoint,
Andy,
we're always looking for opportunities
to enhance the value of the enterprise,
and that's really part
of our business model.
What you see in the first quarter
for incremental investments,
some of that was investments
we were taking to accelerate growth,
and that was really lined up
with what we had shared last December
of the incremental $100 million
over the course of 2017
to deliver accelerated growth
throughout the year.
The other context I'd share with you
in thinking about this step-up
in strategic investments.
If you think back to last March
at our investor meeting
when we laid out
our five-year plan,
we shared plans
for optimizing our portfolio
and supply chain footprint
with, at that time,
what we described,
a total of between
$500 and $600 million
of investments,
and ultimately
that we expected that
by 2020
to be creating
$125 to $175 million
of annualized benefit,
operating income benefit.
What you're seeing
in this step-up
of accelerated strategic investments,
both for the quarter
and for the year,
is us taking more action
related to that,
what we laid out last year
for the optimized actions
on our supply chain footprint.
Yeah, Joe,
as the quarter went on,
it was consistent strength
across the quarter,
all three months
of the quarter.
And I'd further add,
we're seeing April,
the start of April,
tracking very much in line
with what we've been seeing
for the first quarter.
So, really no
inter-quarter
trend changes.
Yeah, Julian,
we're not fundamentally
seeing any change
in our pricing power.
That remains strong.
We do continue
to look for targeted places
where we can
use price
to help drive
organic volume growth.
If I look out
over total 2017,
we're still,
we're expecting
U.S. price growth
to be approximately flat.
If I expand it
to the total globe,
if I pull out
the FX impact,
we expect pricing
to be up slightly.
Our normal range
is 30 to 50 basis points
of core price growth.
I think it'll be
somewhere between there
and flat
for total 2017.
Yeah,
the $136 million
in strategic investments
in the first quarter,
Julian,
a little less
than half of that
is investments
that we see
having a fairly
short-term return
in 2017
and then
into early 2018.
And those are
primarily growth-oriented
investments
and those growth-oriented
were factored
into the guidance
we set out
for the year.
The remainder
of the strategic investments,
those relate
to our portfolio,
supply chain footprint,
and that's really
laid out,
aligned closely
with the plan
that we put forward.
Yeah,
so when we,
in December
when we laid out
our guidance,
EPS guidance
for the year,
strategic investments
we had
incrementally
in a 5 to 10 cent range.
that was aligned
primarily
or almost exclusively
with our
growth investments.
Now what you're seeing,
we're seeing the growth
investments play out
exactly as we guided,
still in that 5 to 10 cent range
for the total year.
What we're layering
on top of that
is additional footprint
actions that were,
and portfolio actions
that were taken
throughout 2017.
So on top
of the growth investments,
there's roughly
an incremental
10 cents
of supply chain
and portfolio actions
that we took
in the first quarter
of 2017.
And then in terms
of the guidance
for the bounce
of this year,
for Q2,
3,
and 4,
there's an extra
40 to 45 cents
on top of that
that was not part
of our initial guidance.
So all in,
the growth investments,
the incremental
10 that we took
in the first quarter
plus what we're expecting
Q2 through Q4,
it's now in the range
of 55 to 65 cents
for the total year.
Nigel,
we're always,
as I said earlier,
we're always looking
for opportunities.
The level
that we were investing
in Q1
in strategic investments
around growth,
no pull forward there.
That's coming
exactly as we had planned.
The increased
strategic investments
around portfolio actions
and supply chain footprint,
that's aligned
with our longer term vision.
The exact timing
of when we were
going to do that,
we did not have clarity
on until we started
pulling the trigger
on some of those actions
in the first quarter
and some that we expect
to have happen
over the next three quarters.
So I'm not sure
I'd characterize it
as a pull forward
as much as it would be.
Now is the time
that it looked like
the right time
for us to pull
the trigger on actions
that we had laid out
last March.
No,
the 40 to 45 cents
does not include
anything for Scott Safety.
At the time
that closes,
we will update guidance
to take into account
any impact
that we'll have
on our 2017 earnings.
In our industrial channel,
we are seeing
increased confidence
in the channel,
which we are seeing,
while we're seeing
good sellouts
of our product,
we're seeing
even stronger sell
into the industrial channel,
primarily in the U.S.
So that is one place
where we're attributing
it to higher confidence
amongst that channel
and seeing what appears
to be some restocking
of depleted channel levels
that we've seen
in the past.
Jeff,
to your first question
on the tax rate
for what we're now seeing
for total 2017,
there's a few dynamics
going on.
First of all,
we are seeing
a favorable
geographic profit mix
for us
that is helping us
in our tax rate.
It's been a headwind
for us the last
couple of years,
and that's switching over
to a tailwind
for us this year.
We're also seeing
some of the benefits
as you'd expect
from some of our
tax planning,
but one of the more
significant items
just in the first quarter
is the benefit
we're getting
from the accounting
standard change
that came into effect
last year
for the excess tax benefits
from stock-based compensation.
from a year-on-year basis,
that's about
a four-cent benefit
versus what we had
a year ago.
And,
Jeff,
I'd say that's
the wild card.
Other things
are going
very much
as we had planned
to get to the
27% tax rate
by 2020,
but with the
added variability
from what happens
with this excess
tax benefit
from stock-based
compensation,
there'll be
some quarters
that's a benefit
and some quarters
we won't see
any benefit at all.
All in,
we're well on track
for hitting
the 27%
in 2020,
possibly even
lower than that,
but when we have
better clarity
on that,
we'll give a revised
number of
can that go
even lower
than the 27%.
To the
second point
on the
strategic
investments,
the $136 million,
of the growth-related
investments,
you're correct,
health care
had the
majority
of that.
There were
small amounts,
single digits
of millions
of dollars,
low to
mid-single digits
and millions
of dollars
in the other
four business
groups,
and then
from a
portfolio
and supply
chain footprint
optimization,
the vast
majority of
that is
impacting
the
electronics
and energy
business
with a little
of that
hitting the
consumer
and office
business,
the consumer
business group.
Yeah,
Rob,
we,
as far as
the automation
portion of our
CapEx spending,
a year ago
at our investor
meeting,
we laid out
that we
expected that
to be
a noticeable
part of our
CapEx investments.
What we're
seeing is
that's playing
out exactly
as we laid
out a year
ago,
that we're
seeing
continued
opportunities
for automation
investments
within our
CapEx plans,
and I
wouldn't call
it an
uptick,
but I'd
say it's
playing out
exactly as
we laid
out.
Supply
chain and
portfolio
optimization,
and much
less around
growth.
If we
see growth
even higher
than what
we're currently
expecting,
could our
growth
investments
tick up
some?
I think
the short
answer is
yes,
it could
tick up
some,
but I
don't think
on a
material
basis.
I think
we're now
talking
single digits
of pennies
at that
point.
thanks,
Steve.
Yeah,
Steve,
thanks for
the question.
Part of
what we
talked about
a little
over a
year ago
at our
outlook
meeting for
the five-year
outlook
meeting is
the number
of manufacturing
sites we
have around
the world
and looking
at the
productivity
in those
sites and
the opportunity
we have
through
rationalizing
the number
of those
sites,
increasing
capital into
some of
our more
productive
sites,
the opportunity
to reduce
the total
footprint of
our manufacturing
and supply
chain
sites over
the course
of the next
four years.
So that's
what we mean
when we talk
about it
when we
laid out
a $500
to $600
million investment
that we
expect to
take.
The resulting
productivity
from that
that by
the time
we get
to 2020
we think
that will
add another
$125 to
$175
million of
added operating
income to
that productivity
we can get
through.
Look at this
globally,
Steve.
We had a
positive,
though very
small price
in all
businesses
except for
healthcare
where we
were flat.
To the
first question
on business,
and I'll go
further in
geography,
we expect
that this
action that
we're taking
in the
second quarter
and in
the third
and fourth
quarter
will impact
all businesses
and all
geographies,
that it will
be broad.
As far as
the specific
details of
each business,
we're still
working through
those details.
We're not
ready to be
sharing that
yet,
Lawrence.
And then
as far as
the 17
to 18,
some of
these actions
will have
a tail
into 18
where there
will be
residual cost
impact
hitting us
in 18,
though I
expect it
will not,
I very much
expect it
will be a
decline from
the level
that we're
projecting now
for 2017.
you.